Finding Aid for Stefan S. Fajans papers, 1943-2012
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Stefan S. Fajans papers 1943-2012
Fajans, Stefan S.
2015024 Aa 2
Stefan S. Fajans was a Professor of Internal Medicine at the University of Michigan Medical School from 1949-1988 and active Professor Emeritus of Internal Medicine until 2014. The collection includes personal correspondence during his time in the U.S. Army Medical Corps in World War II, as well as materials related to his professional activities and interests, including patient records, correspondence, lectures, manuscripts and other topical files related to his research on diabetes, especially Maturity Onset Diabetes of the Young (MODY).
4.5 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Donated by Stefan S. Fajans (donor no. 11141 ) in July, 2014.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
Portions of the collection (boxes 3-5) are subject to client/patient restrictions and are closed for one hundred years from date of creation.
Stefan S. Fajans was born on March 15, 1918 in Munich, Germany, and immigrated to Ann Arbor, Michigan with his family at the age of 18 when his father, Kasimir, a physical chemist and pioneer in the science of radioactivity, joined the faculty of the University of Michigan. He became a naturalized citizen in 1942. In 1947, he married Ruth Stine, a biochemist and University of Michigan alumna, at her parent's home in Washington D.C. Their marriage lasted 64 years, until she passed away at the age of 89. They had two sons, Peter (Daniar) and John (Luanne), and three grandchildren.
Dr. Fajans received his Bachelor of Science in chemistry in 1938 from the University of Michigan. He entered medical school at the University of Michigan that same year. After taking an elective in endocrinology that was taught by Dr. Jerome Conn, he became interested in endocrinology and, more specifically, in the control of carbohydrate metabolism. He earned his Doctor of Medicine in 1942.
In 1943, after completing an internship at Mount Sinai Hospital in New York City, he was drafted into the U.S. Army Medical Corps during World War II. He was a member of the 41st Evacuation Hospital, which was the first to arrive on Omaha Beach, three days after the Normandy invasion.
Following the end of the war, Dr. Fajans returned to the University of Michigan where he completed a residency in internal medicine and a fellowship in endocrinology under Dr. Conn. Dr. Fajans joined the University of Michigan faculty as an instructor in 1949; he was promoted to assistant professor in 1951, associate professor in 1955, and professor in 1961.
Dr. Fajans is well known for his research on diabetes, making "novel contributions to the knowledge that diabetes was not a single disease, but consisted of several subtypes with different causes". In 1958, Dr. Fajans began studying a Michigan family, the "R-W pedigree," with more than 360 members spanning seven generations, 76 of whom had a form of non-insulin-dependent diabetes. However, the disease "appeared unusually early in this family -- diagnosed in children and adolescents, unlike the usual onset of type 2 diabetes after age 40". As a result of this research, he was the first to describe a subtype of type 2 diabetes, Maturity-Onset Diabetes of the Young (MODY). During the late 1980s, Dr. Fajans began collaborating with Dr. Graeme Bell at the University of Chicago, co-publishing the first paper to describe a genetic marker of MODY and the gene itself.
Throughout his career, Dr. Fajans received many awards and honors. In 1973, he was named Chief of the Division of Endocrinology and Metabolism, and in 1977 he became the first director of the Michigan Diabetes Research and Training Center, having been instrumental in its establishment. He was president of the American Diabetes Association, 1971--1972, and vice president of the Endocrine Society the preceding year. He gave the Banting Memorial Lecture --the highest award bestowed by the Diabetes UK, the United Kingdom's leading diabetes charity-- in the USA, Canada, and Great Britain. He was the University of Michigan's Henry Russell Lecturer in 1983, and was named a Master Fellow of the American College of Physicians in 1984 and a Senior Member of the Institute of Medicine of the National Academy of Sciences in 1985. The Stefan S. Fajans/Glaxo Smith Klein Professorship in Diabetes was established in 2003 and the annual Stefan S. Fajans Lectureship in Diabetes in 2010 to pay tribute to his accomplishments.
Dr. Fajans continued his research program on MODY even after his official retirement in 1988. He remained Professor Emeritus of Internal Medicine until his death on June 22, 2014.
The Stefan S. Fajans papers are comprised of personal correspondence with his family while in the U.S. Army Medical Corps during World War II as well as a wide range of materials documenting his professional life. The latter are a rich source for his research on Maturity Onset Diabetes of the Young (MODY) and its associated genetic markers. The Stefan S. Fajans papers are divided into two series: Personal Correspondence and Professional Files.
Subjects:
Conn, Jerome W., 1907-; Diabetes--Genetic aspects.; Endocrinology.; Fajans, Stefan S.; Non-insulin-dependent diabetes.; United States. Army Medical Department (1968- ); University of Michigan. Department of Internal Medicine.; University of Michigan. Diabetes Research and Training Center.; World War, 1939-1945.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Personal Correspondence
  The Personal Correspondence (1993-1945, 0.1 linear feet) series includes correspondence with his family while in the U.S. Army Medical Corps during World War II. The letters detail his daily life and work in multiple locations in Europe.
  - World War II Correspondence 1943-1945, 2 folders (Box 1)
- Professional Files 1950-2012
  The Professional Files (1950-2012, 4.4 linear feet) include patient records covering his research on the R-W Pedigree and MODY. These records are predominately from his time as an active professor at the University of Michigan, although a number of records exist from research he did after retirement. They also include topical files, mostly correspondence with colleagues, sorted alphabetically. Dr. Fajans kept a significant topical file on Dr. Conn, his mentor for his research assistantship and lifelong colleague and friend. Finally, they include outlines of lectures he gave on all aspects of Diabetes and its subtypes, sorted alphabetically (sometimes listed by title of lecture, and sometimes by location) as well as a manuscripts and reprints of many of his publications on MODY and its genetic markers.
  - Topical Files
    - 50 Years of MODY Research 2008 (Box 1)
    - Aberdeen 1968 (Box 1)
    - Arvam, Peter 2009 (Box 1)
    - Conn, Jerome
      - Alumni Society 2009 (Box 1)
      - Biographical Sketch and Publications 1977 (Box 1)
      - Correspondence 1961-1994, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Memorial
        - Memorial 1994 (Box 1)
        - Memorial Convocation 1994, 2 folders (Box 1)
        - Memorial Programs and Brochures 1974, 1994 (Box 1)
      - Symposium and Pictures undated (Box 1)
        (Contains photos of Jerome Conn)
    - D (various topics) 2000-2009 (Box 1)
    - Davos 1987 (Box 1)
    - Diabetes Outlook 1976-1977 (Box 1)
    - Doniach, Deborah 1976-1979 (Box 1)
    - European Association for the Study of Diabetes Membership 1997 (Box 1)
    - F (various topics) 1975 (Box 1)
    - Fellows 2009 (Box 1)
    - Final Program 1985 (Box 1)
    - Gestational Diabetes 2007-2009 (Box 1)
    - Hattersby, Andrew 1998-1999, 2002, 2009, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - I (various topics) 2009 (Box 1)
    - Insulinoma Patients 1984 (Box 1)
    - Kahn, Richard 2009 (Box 1)
    - L (various topics) 1987-1988 (Box 1)
    - Licenses 2012 (Box 1)
    - Long-Term Study of Asymptomatic and Future Diabetes 2005-2008, 9 folders (Box 5)
    - Michigan Diabetes Association 1971-1973, 2006 (Box 1)
    - MODY 1983 (Box 4)
      [CR RESTRICTED until July 1 2114 ]
    - MODY 4 2010 (Box 4)
    - MODY, GTT undated (Box 4)
    - MODYs as Paradigm of the Pathogenesis of Type 2 Diabetes 1998 (Box 1)
    - N (various topics) 1975, 1999 (Box 1)
    - Northern Illinois Diabetes Association 1988 (Box 1)
    - P (various topics) 1977-2000, 7 folders (Box 1)
    - Porte, Jr., Daniel 1985-1987 (Box 1)
    - Professorship (Box 1)
    - R (various topics) 1965-1988, 4 folders (Box 1)
    - Rinke 1964, 2007, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Romanian Academy of Medical Sciences 2002 (Box 1)
    - S (various topics) 1990 (Box 1)
    - Selecting Criteria for the Diagnosis of "Diabetes Mellitus" 1980 (Box 1)
    - Strong, James 1991 (Box 1)
    - T (various topics) 1977-1988 (Box 1)
    - Tattersall, Robert 1976-2002 (Box 1)
    - U (various topics) 2000 (Box 1)
    - V (various topics) 1977-1988 (Box 1)
    - W (various topics) 1981 (Box 1)
    - Weigand 1982 (Box 4)
    - Weiland, Otto 1985-1986 (Box 1)
    - Williams, Robert 1970-1976 (Box 1)
    - X, Y, Z (various topics) 1983-2000, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Yalow, Rosalyn 1964, 1972 (Box 1)
  - Lectures, Outlines, Etc.
    - ADA Postgrad 1983 (Box 1)
    - Banting Lecture 1978 (Box 1)
    - Classification of Diabetes Mellitus 1981 (Box 1)
    - Current Concepts in the Recognition, Localization and Management of Organic Hyperinsulinism 1981 (Box 1)
    - Diabetes 1973 (Box 1)
    - Diabetes Mellitus 1968, 1975 (Box 1)
    - Diabetes Update 1983 (Box 1)
    - Early Stages of Diabetes: Definitions and Present Concepts undated (Box 1)
    - Evanston Hospital 1982 (Box 1)
    - Freiburg, Germany 1981 (Box 1)
    - Hawaii 1983 (Box 1)
    - Henry Russell Lecture 1983 (Box 1)
    - Heterogeneity of Diabetes Mellitus undated (Box 1)
    - Idiopathic Diabetes Mellitus (Box 2)
      - Clinical and Etiological Heterogeneity of Diabetes Mellitus 1980-1982 (Box 2)
      - Current Concepts of the Pathogenesis of Diabetic Complications undated (Box 2)
      - Current Status of Glucose Tolerance Tests 1967 (Box 2)
      - Diagnosis of Diabetes: Concepts and Controversies 1976 (Box 2)
      - Genetic and Environmental Factors in the Pathogenesis of Diabetes Mellitus 1976 (Box 2)
      - Heterogeneity of Diabetes Mellitus in Man undated (Box 2)
      - Minimum Requirements for the Diagnosis and Treatment of Diabetes 1976 (Box 2)
    - Life Sciences 1993 (Box 2)
    - Los Angeles 1979 (Box 2)
    - Macomb Hospital 1983 (Box 2)
    - Marseille 1978 (Box 2)
    - Nairobi 1982 (Box 2)
    - Outlines undated, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Relationship of Blood Sugar Control to the Complications of Diabetes undated (Box 2)
    - Saginaw 1981 (Box 2)
    - Sendai, Japan 1982 (Box 2)
    - Spontaneous Hypoglycemia undated (Box 2)
    - Toronto 1984 (Box 2)
    - Ulm 1997 (Box 2)
    - Vail 1984 (Box 2)
  - Manuscripts, Publications, Reprints, etc.
    - Biographical Sketch undated (Box 2)
    - Curriculum Vitae and Bibliography 2008 (Box 2)
    - Manuscripts 2001, 2009, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Publications 1986-2009, 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Reprints 1981 (Box 2)
  - Patient Records 1950-2012
    (There is an index at the front of each book.)
    - Fajan's Research Patient Printout 1987, 2 folders (Box 3)
      [CR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2087 ]
    - Book 1 1950-1988 (Box 3)
      [CR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2088 ]
    - Book 2 1952-1992 (Box 3)
      [CR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2092 ]
    - Books 3-4 1954-1996 (Box 3)
      [CR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2096 ]
    - Books 5-6 1955-1989 (Box 3)
      [CR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2089 ]
    - Book 7 1957-2003 (Box 3)
      [CR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2103 ]
    - Books 8-9 1958-1996 (Box 3)
    - Book 10, 1960-2003 (Box 3)
    - Book 11 1962-1989, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Book 12 1964-2004, 2 folders (Box 3)
      [CR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2104 ]
    - Book 13 1966-1985, 3 folders (Box 4)
      [CR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2085 ]
    - Book 14 1969-1996, 3 folders (Box 4)
      [CR RESTRICTED until July 1, 20096 ]
    - Book 15 1972-1987, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Book 16 1967-2004, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Book 17 1977-1985, 2 folders (Box 4)
      [CR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2114 ]
    - Book 18 1982-2012, 2 folders (Box 4)
      [CR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2112 ]
    - Wiegand Book 1983-2007, 3 folders (Box 4)
      [CR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2107 ]
    - Pratt Book 1993-2007 (Box 4)
    - Rinke Book 1991-1994 (Box 4)
      [CR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2094 ]
Relared Material
The Bentley Historical Library holds the News and Information Services (University of Michigan) Faculty and Staff Files, which include a folder for Dr. Fajans.
The Bentley Historical Library also holds the Linda Kay Tanner Strodtman papers, which include mention of Dr. Fajans in the 1976-1983 subseries of the Michigan Diabetes Research and Training Center (MDRTC) series and the Diabetes Center Unit (DCU), MDRTC series.
Finally, the Bentley Historical Library holds the Center for the History of Medicine (University of Michigan) Oral History Interviews, which include an oral history recording of Dr. Fajans.